Finding Aid for Dramatic Arts Center Records 1954-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dramatic Arts Center Records 1954-1966, 1955-1960
Dramatic Arts Center.
2 linear feet
Corporation established in 1954 to operate a center for dramatic and theater arts in Ann Arbor, Michigan. DAC also sought unsuccessfully to establish repertory theater in Ann Arbor. The Center dissolved in 1967. records accumulated by DAC secretary and president Wilfred Kaplan. Included are background information consisting of bylaws and chronology of DAC; administrative records; activities materials concerning work of the Steering Committee for a Repertory Theater; publicity, programs, and other materials relating to DAC productions; and scrapbooks containing clippings, programs, and one photograph.
0073 Bp 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
These records were transferred in a donation from Prof. Wilfred Kaplan (donor 8901 ) in 1999.
The record group is open for research.
The Ann Arbor Dramatic Arts Center (DAC) was created in May 1954 as a nonprofit corporation to "operate a Center for dramatic and other arts, a professional theater, theater and dance classes for the children, and a place for exhibit of works of art" (Box 1, Background folder). Its purpose was to encourage an interest and participation, in Ann Arbor and its community, in the arts, and to provide facilities for such a development.
Many of the essential components of the DAC had already been proposed by the Arts Theater Club. Launched around 1950, its goal was the production of plays in a small arena theater in Ann Arbor. The plays they performed were varied and drew good audiences, but the project ultimately failed due apparently to bad management.
From 1954 to 1957 the DAC maintained a professional arena theater in Ann Arbor, under the directorship of Joseph Gistirack. During each of these seasons of approximately twenty-five weeks, the DAC presented many plays of enduring value, among which stand out "The Moon in the Yellow River," "A Sleep of Prisoners," "Topaze," "Pygmalion," "The Confidential Clerk," and "The Importance of Being Earnest."
In 1957 the professional theater was suspended partly because the lease for the theater space in the Old Masonic Temple on Fourth Avenue could not be extended, and partly because of doubts about the ability of local sponsors to take care of the recurring deficit.
The organizational structure was maintained and the board of directors continued to meet on a monthly basis, with an executive committee conducting affairs between meetings. The DAC presented, with considerable success, several childrens plays through Junior Theater, and a program of Saturday classes for children in art, dance, and theater, was established with the collaboration of the public schools. These classes, too, enjoyed great popularity. There were several programs in music and dance, both of which were important ingredients in the dramatic performances.
Interest in the theater, dance, and arts continued to grow steadily in Ann Arbor, as evidenced by the success of productions of the Drama Season and the University of Michigan Speech Department, those of the Civic Theater, and programs sponsored by the Ann Arbor Civic Ballet. In view of this, the DAC launched an ambitious project to bring a repertory theater to Ann Arbor, similar to the one established in Stratford, Ontario. Contacts were made and in September of 1958, the DAC was approached by Oliver Rea, a theater promoter from New York. Mr. Rea was working with Tyrone Guthrie, then considered by many to be the leading director in the English-speaking theater and first artistic director of the Stratford Festival. Dr. Guthrie wished to found a similar project in an American city and had heard of interest in Ann Arbor.
The DAC took upon itself the organization of a support group to bring Guthrie's theater to Ann Arbor. Both Mr. Rea and Dr. Guthrie visited Ann Arbor in October 1959 as guests of the DAC. Dr. Guthrie gave a forceful presentation about his plans but the reception from University officials was cool. By the time the initial reluctance was overcome and a firm interest was shown, it was too late. Minneapolis was chosen to house Dr. Guthrie's theater.
The DAC continued with its activities, promoting and presenting plays to the Ann Arbor community until its dissolution in 1967.
The records of the Ann Arbor Dramatic Arts Center were accumulated and maintained by DAC secretary and president Professor Wilfred Kaplan. The records cover the period 1954 to 1966, are arranged in five series: Background, Administrative, Activities, Production, and Scrapbooks. The records, consisting of correspondence, memoranda, and other files, detail the formation of the Dramatic Arts Centers, its activities, its planning for a theater in Ann Arbor, and its eventual demise.
Subjects:
Dramatic Arts Center.; Repertory theater--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Theater--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Dramatic Arts Center.; Theatrical productions--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Children--Performances & portrayals.
Contributors:
Kaplan, Wilfred, 1915-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Background
  The Background series includes bylaws and a chronology of the DAC.
  - Bylaws, amendments, and a chronology 1955, undated (Box 1)
- Administrative
  The Administrative series is composed of the usual organizational materials: agendas and minutes, newsletters, correspondence, and reports. A substantive part of this series is the long run of minutes of the Board of Directors from 1955 to 1967. Arranged in chronological order by year, these records summarize the activities and concerns of the DAC very thoroughly. They also show the structure of the organization in any given year. Although not every year is consistently documented, these minutes provide an invaluable retrospective source showing how the DAC changed and evolved over the course of time.
  Also illuminating within the Administrative series, despite the obvious chronological gaps, are the general correspondence and the financial records. All of these records are arranged by year in ascending order. Given that these records span from the founding of the DAC in 1954 up to the mid 1960s, they complement the set of minutes and fill in the details that these can only summarize. The correspondence mainly documents two things: 1) organizational structure and 2) the DAC's relationship with other individuals, associations, agencies, or institutions.
  - Agendas and minutes 1955-1967 (Box 1)
  - The American National Theater and Academy (ANTA) 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Dance Theater 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Annual meeting
    - 1955-1957, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1959, 1964, 1965, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Buildings undated (Box 1)
  - Civic Theater 1960-1968, undated (Box 1)
  - Destine Dance Company 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Employment opportunities 1956 (Box 1)
  - Finances 1954-1966 (Box 1)
  - Foundations undated (Box 1)
  - General correspondence 1954-1967, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters to members 1954-1967 (Box 1)
  - Lists for sponsoring campaign undated (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Operations 1954-1966 (Box 1)
  - Phoenix Theater 1960 (Box 1)
  - Publicity
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - News releases 1960, 1961, undated (Box 1)
  - Ypsilanti Greek Theater 1964 (Box 1)
- Activities
  In the Activities series, the Steering Committee for a Repertory Theater materials is comprised of proposals, reports, and correspondence that represents an excellent way to understand the evolution of the DAC's project to establish a professional theater in Ann Arbor. Another project the DAC tackled was the Long Range Plan to guarantee the successful and lasting presence of a theater group in Ann Arbor.
  - Long Range Plan
    - Correspondence 1956-1958 (Box 1)
    - General 1956, undated (Box 1)
  - Steering Committee for a Repertory Theater
    - Correspondence 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence about Oliver Rea's visit to Ann Arbor 1959-1961 (Box 1)
    - Letters in support 1959 (Box 1)
    - Minutes and reports 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Proposals 1959, undated (Box 1)
    - Publicity
      - Clippings (Box 1)
      - Lists undated (Box 1)
- Productions
  In the Productions series the materials gathered are very important to understand the wide range of plays the DAC promoted. There are programs of the plays, as well as posters and newspaper clippings with reviews of some of the plays the DAC performed over the seasons it was active. Junior theater and its productions for children are also well documented.
  - Junior Theater 1956-1966 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1955-1961, undated (Box 1)
  - Plays (Box 1)
  - Programs 1954-1957 (Box 1)
  - Publicity
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Posters 1962, undated (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series consists of three scrapbooks containing newspaper articles and programs of productions. There is one photograph of a children's production of Hansel and Gretel in 1954.
  - 1954-circa 1964, 3 volumes (Box 2)